If it's for performance purely, it would
be smarter to drop out.
But that's not who I am.
I like to do things not only because I
want to try to win the race,
but it's more about trying to explore my
body physiology, training and all that.
And injuries and
problems are part of our lives.
It gives me a lot of freedom to
experiment about those things,
trying to say, "Okay, let's go to a race
injured and see how
we can deal with things.
And I have done that for all my career.
So tell me.
It's alright.
Yesterday I did 90k running
And I don't feel more
pain or the muscles are okay.
And it's more when I go fast.
And downhill, uphill?
downhill
So do you feel that it
has been, that it's milder?
Yeah, it's milder for sure.
And last week you said you did 70k?
Yeah, 70k.
And then this week I did on Monday 50k
And yesterday 90k.
Are we heading in the right direction?
I think it's good.
Then after the race, I don't know.
Well, after the race it's something else.
Yeah.
What's your plan next week?
No, no, it's very easy.
When do you travel?
I'll travel tomorrow.
I think I will see how I feel tomorrow
but so far it's been a good test.
So there is hope.
There is hope,
There is always hope.
Friday evening, one week before the race.
Um, San Francisco and
here in Olympic Valley.
So excited to be back here.
Ah, lots of ice.
Ah, here is less.
We are at Auburn, endurance capital of
the world, I call it.
And here is the stadium.
It is where Western
States finish line is.
And hopefully in one week I
will enter this door here.
To finish the race.
And I'm going to run the
last 20 miles of the race.
Yeah, just to remember a bit how it looks
like, how it feels like.
I have a last
training day before the race.
It's called now NN 202.
It's a prototype that we have been
working for doing like
more long distance races.
I have been running
like yeah, I think, yeah.
Probably like, I don't know,
700-800 kilometers on them.
So, yeah, it's well tested though.
Mile 99 flag.
Last training before the race
and yeah, it's feeling good.
It's not super hot.
So, it's a good
feeling to not feel too warm.
And yeah, a big one on staurday
Back to the track.
Yeah, a bit excited.
I think we'll really come like probably
like Friday evening.
Now it's kind of, yeah,
been there, been here.
But yeah, it's nice to be back.
So, yeah, now I just
need to rest as well.
See how tomorrow feels, the TFL,
but I think it's pretty okay.
So, I was measuring the sodium
concentration to see any day ratio like
strategy during the race.
those years were years of ambition.
Prepairing all the food and we
start like on the first hours with mix of
fats and some carbs like
50-50 or even a little more.
And then transitioning towards the end
with it's more like fully carbs.
So, it's kind of a transition from a mix
to when we are in a pace that is slow so
we are not utilizing a lot of carbs
towards the end of the race where it will
be more carb utilization and changing on
that through the race.
Before they go to bed.
Hey, hello.
How do you feel?
Ah, good, yeah. It's very cold actually.
Yes, I've heard
Yeah, yeah, it's like not even 30
degrees. It looks like in Auburn.
And how do you, what will be your
strategy? Will you try to not
let anyone escape this year?
Yeah, I will see because I
think in the uphills I can push.
In the downhills I need to be very
careful with the knee, I think
not to try to go too fast.
So, probably will try to make it a bit
hard on the uphills and then down like to
be a bit more strategic
and then see how I feel.
But yeah, I think it will be fast because
it's cold so people are
not really blowing up.
I almost expected it warmer because if it's
harder I think it's better for me.
It's exciting. It's 30 minutes to start
and it's cold. It's a lot of wind so it
will be an interesting race.
I'm feeling excited. These first four or
five hours they are already like, you
want to get there because you are running
slow and it's nothing really happening.
But yeah, excited to start
and to get to back to the mountains.
Three, two, one.
[Cheering]
[Music]
We all share the same passion for being
in the trails, for the effort, for
dreaming about something and putting the
effort to achieve it.
And that's like, it makes me love this
sport. It's about witnessing people,
achieving their dreams.
[Music]
A great run. Jennifer Lichter not far
behind. 20 seconds at the last hill.
Looks like Killan
walking the opposite direction.
Not a good sign.
might be cutting a wristband off.
Which is the saddest way
to be pulled from a race.
Yeah.
Getting that wristband
clipped hurts pretty bad.
[Music]
My race was, I wouldn't say completely
unexpected because it was a gamble.
I knew that I came here with the problem
in the knee and I
wanted to try and I did that.
So I am happy for this. Even if, yeah,
the outcome is not the one I wish for,
but that's racing is part of the game, is
part of competition to just show up and
try and get the best
and that's what I did.
But the conditions made that it was super
fast. We were like flying from the start
and I was feeling great.
But after like mile 30, I started to
really feel like first my knee is super
stiff and then a lot of pain.
So it was not possible to continue, but
that at the end allowed me to go and
spectate on the race.
And like it was an incredible race. Like
it was an edition that it will be
remembered for decades.
Like I think it was one generation that
we saw the runs of Scott Jurek and
Antrejeson and like that
inspire our generation.
And I think the next generation got
inspired by like the 2010 race that it
was shown in Unbreakable.
And I think this year, this race will be
remembered for
generations because it was just.
An amazing competition, such a deep field
and we were like following the race.
We went to Forest Hill and then to
Pointed Rocks and
then to the finish line.
And like both the men and the women's top
five, they were so, so close and they
were so, so fast breaking both male and
female record doing such amazing times.
It was incredible. It was just like I
kind of like I'm happy that I drop out
and I could witness
like history on the trail.
Before being an athlete,
I'm a fan of the sport
I love seeing
runners racing, cruising it.
I see I love being on the on the Golden
Hour in the Western States, seeing the
last finishes, seeing
everyone at the end.
And sometimes I'm pushing to my
dreams and sometimes it's others the dreams
that you witness and you see and you are
so happy for them, for friends that I
know and for people that I
have no idea was their name.
But you see them like crossing the line
and it's just like so amazing.
It's about that. I think at the end it's
not about like performing for oneself.
But before that, it's about like sharing
what we love that it's be out in the
mountains with people
that like the same things.
I think it will be
fast because it's cold
so like people is not
really blowing up
so that's...
I expected it warmer
because like if it's
harder I think
it's better for me